# Massimiliano Russo

Email: m\_russo@hms.harvard.edu Homepage: https://rmassimiliano.github.io

ORCID: 0000-0003-4953-9341

### Current position

Postdoctoral research fellow, Harvard Medical School program in Therapeutic Sciences within the Harvard-MIT Center for Regulatory Science, I am also part of Prof. Lorenzo Trippa's group at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute (DFCI) department of Data Science.

Research interests Analysis and design of clinical trials; Decision theory; Bayesian nonparametrics; Tensor factorization; Categorical variables; Hierarchical models; Models for latent variables; Machine learning and Data mining; Computational statistics.

#### Education

2015–2019 PhD in Statistical Sciences, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences,

Thesis: Bayesian inference for tensor factorization models.

Advisor: Bruno Scarpa

2013-2015 Master in Statistical Sciences, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical

Sciences, Final Mark: 110/110 cum laude,

Thesis: Olfactory perception differences in Italian regions: a nonparametric

Bayesian approach to tensor factorization.

Advisor: Bruno Scarpa; Co-advisor: Giancarlo Ottaviano

2009-2013 Bachelor in Statistical and Actuarial sciences, Università degli Studi del

Sannio, Benevento, Final Mark: 110/110 cum laude,

Thesis: Multivariate robust estimation.

Advisor: Luca Greco

## **Awards**

Best poster award, second place winner for "Inference in Response-Adaptive Clinical Trials When the Enrolled Population Varies Over Time", ASA Biopharmaceutical Section Regulatory-Industry Statistics Workshop 2020

Best paper award for "Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data" Dept. of Statistical Sciences, University of Padova (Research Prize 2018)

Winner of the 3 minutes thesis competition selection of Dept. of Statistical Sciences, University of Padova, October 19, 2018.

Young researcher travel award ISBA2018, Edinburgh, United Kingdom.

Travel support for COBAL V (2017), Guanajuato, Mexico

Young researcher travel award ISBA2016, Sardinia, Italy.

#### Academic experience

Published Papers Refereed Journals Rigon, T., Aliverti, E., Russo, M., and Scarpa, B., A discussion on: "Centered partition processes: Informative priors for clustering" by Paganin, S., Herring, A. H., Olshan, A. F. and Dunson, D. B., Bayesian Analysis, 2021+, accepted for publication.

Ottaviano, G., Nardello, E., Pendolino, A. L., Pozza, M. D., Russo, M., Savietto, E. Peter, J. A., Ermolao, A., Nasal Function Changes at High Altitude, American Journal of Rhinology & Allergy, 34(5) 618-625, 2020.

Aliverti, E., Paganin, S., Rigon, T. and Russo, M., A discussion on: Latent nested nonparametric priors by Camerlenghi, F., Dunson, D.B., Lijoi, A., Prünster, I. and Rodriguez, A., Bayesian Analysis, 14 (4) 1303 - 1356, 2019.

Ottaviano, G., Pendolino, A. L., Nardello, E., Maculan, P., Martini, A., Russo, M. and Lund, V. J., Peak nasal inspiratory flow measurement and visual analogue scale in a large adult population, Clinical Otolaryngology; 44: 541-548, doi:10.1111/coa.13329., 2019.

Russo, M., Durante, D. & Scarpa, B., Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, Computational Statistics & Data Analysis. 126, 136-149, 2018.

Cantone E., Ciofalo A., Vodicka J., Iacono V., Mylonakis I., Scarpa B., Russo M., lengo M., de Vincentiis M., Martini A. and Ottaviano G., Pleasantness of olfactory and trigeminal stimulants in different Italian regions., European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology, 1–7, 2017.

Book Chapters Cabassi, A., Casa, A., Fontana, M., Russo, M., and Farcomeni, A., Three & testing perspectives on connectome data, Springer Proceedings in Mathematics Proceedings & Statistics, vol 257, 37–55. Springer, Cham, 2018.

> Russo, M., Detecting Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, Proceedings the Italian Statistical Society, Firenze University Press, 2017.

Under Review

Aliverti, E. and Russo M., Dynamic modeling of the Italians' attitude towards Covid-19, (submitted).

Russo M. and Scarpa B., Learning in medicine: the importance of statistical thinking, (submitted).

Russo, M., Ventz, S., Wang, V., Trippa, L., Inference in response-adaptive clinical trials when the enrolled population varies over time, Biometrics, invited revision.

Aliverti, E. and Russo M., Stratified stochastic variational inference for highdimensional network factor model, arXiv preprint, arXiv:2006.14217, Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics, invited revision.

Russo, M., Singer, B. H. & Dunson, D. B., Multivariate mixed membership modeling: Inferring domain-specific risk profiles, arXiv preprint, arXiv:1901.05191, The Annals of Applied Statistics, invited revision.

Teaching

Parallel Computing for big data analysis, March 2018, Specialist lectures during the class of Statistical Methods for Big Data Analysis of Prof. Bruno Scarpa, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Padova, Italy.

Introduction to real analysis (B.Sc.), Year 2014/2015, Academic Tutor, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Padova, Italy.

Advanced statistical inference (M.Sc.), Year 2014/2015, Academic Tutor, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Padova, Italy.

Talks Invited in the session "Using external data in adaptive clinical trial design", at ISBA world meeting 2021, (ISBA 2021).

Invited in the session "Bayesian non parametrics methods for classification", Classification and Data Analysis Group, (CLADAG 2021).

Inference in clinical trials when the patient population is subject to changes over time, (CMStatistics 2020), (Invited talk).

Session: "Recent developments in Bayesian methodology"

Inference in clinical trials when the patient population is subject to changes over time, Joint Statistical Meeting of the American Statistical Society, (JSM 2020), (Invited talk).

Topic contributed session: "Statistical innovation in regulatory science"

Bayesian optimal sequential futility decisions via auxiliary endpoints, International Biometric Conference, (IBC 2020), Accepted for contributed oral Presentation (selected among 700 submissions).

canceled due to COVID-19

Scalable inference for network factor model, Advanced Statistics for Physics Discovery, Padova, Italy, September 24, 2018, (Contributed talk).

Multivariate mixed membership modeling: Inferring domain-specific risk profiles, IBC2018, Barcellona, Spain, July 10, 2018, (Contributed talk).

Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, COBAL V, Cimat, Guanajuato, Mexico, June 8, 2017, (Contributed talk).

Organized Sessions Advances in Bayesian methods for medical data, Bayesian Young Statisticians Meeting: Online, (BAYSM:O 2020).

Posters Inference in response-adaptive clinical trials when the enrolled population varies over time, 2020 Global Conference on Regulatory Science.

> Inference in response-adaptive clinical trials when the enrolled population varies over time, ASA Biopharmaceutical Section Regulatory-Industry Statistics Workshop 2020.

> Inference in response-adaptive clinical trials when the enrolled population varies over time, DIA Regulatory Science Forum 2020.

> Inference in clinical trials when the patient population is subject to changes over time, HiTS Annual Symposium, Boston, MA, USA, October 21. 2019.

> Soft classification tree ensemble of Higgs pair production, Advanced Statistics for Physics Discovery, Padova, Italy, September 24, 2018.

> Multivariate mixed membership modeling: Inferring domain-specific risk profiles, ISBA2018, Edinburgh, United Kingdom, June 29, 2018.

> A multivariate mixed membership model for malaria risk detection, Obayes2017, Austin, Texas, December 11, 2017.

> Detecting Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, SIS2017, Florence, Italy, June 28, 2017.

> Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, ISBA2016, Sardinia, Italy, June 16, 2016.

Workshops **NIMBLE short course**, UC Berkeley, June 2020, (online).

& 3-day workshop on NIMBLE: a system for building and sharing analysis methods for Summer Schools statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods.

Start-Up Research, University of Siena, Italy, June 2017.

A 2-day meeting where groups of young scholars, advised by senior researchers, were asked to develop innovative methods and models to analyze a common dataset from the Neurosciences.

Data Hackathons

Duke Datathon, Durham, NC, USA, February 2017.

Stats under the stars-3, Firenze, Italy, June 2017.

Stats under the stars, Padova, Italy, September 2015.

Reviewer for: BMC Bioinformatics; Computational Statistics and Data Analysis (CSDA); European Symposium on Artificial Neural Networks (ESANN) 2020; Journal of Computation and Graphical Statistics (JCGS); Journal of Computational Methods in Sciences and Engineering (JCMSE); Journal of Open Source Software (JOSS) Mathematics; Social Indicator Research; Statistical Methods & Applications (SMA); Trials.

Memberships International Society for Bayesian Analysis (ISBA); j-ISBA

#### Outreach & events

Regulatory Science Student & Faculty Mixer (October 2020)

Online meeting with graduate and prospective students to discuss research opportunities.

Regsci Forum: Fellows Showcase. What the Harvard-MIT Center for Regulatory Science actually does? Wonder no more! (January 2020)

Research presentation to describe the world of regulatory science to students.

Big data Biosensori e Biobanche, December 2019

Presentation of my research at Università degli Study del Sannio.

Harvard-MIT Center for Regulatory Science Open House: Learn about RegSci and research opportunity. (September 2019)

Meeting with Harvard graduate students to discuss research opportunities.

Volunteer for Venetonight - La notte dei ricercatori, Padova, Italy. (2015,2016 & 2017)

Developed an online app interfacing with twitter to track and display in real-time the sentiment of the event.

Volunteer for StatisitcAll, Treviso, Italy (2015)

Statistical games and activities to show the magic of statistics to kids and adults.

Volunteer at orientation days for high schools students, Scegli con noi. Campus Agripolis di Legnaro, Padova, Italy. (2015 & 2016)

#### Work experience

Feb. 2019 - Aug. 2019 Data Analyst, WorkFor, WFIT CRM Services, Roma.

Data analysis and consulting.

## Study visits

Nov. 2016 - June 2017 Visiting Research Scholar, Duke University, Department of Statistical Science, Sept. 2017 - Mar. 2018 Durham, NC, USA, under the supervision of prof. David B. Dunson.

#### Languages

Italian: native; English: fluent; French: basic; Spanish: basic.

# Computing skills

Programming languages  $\ R$  (advanced knowledge of Rcpp, tidyverse and shiny libraries);

C/C++,Python, Julia, Matlab, JAVA.

Software SPSS, PSPP, Office,  $\mathrm{SQL}/\mathrm{MYSQL}, \mathrm{Bugs}, \mathrm{Jags}, \mathrm{Stan},$  and  $\mathrm{Nimble}.$ 

Other LATEX, git/github, vim & emacs, bash.

12 April 2021